Good morning, this is Dan Margulies filling in for Rabbi Linzer. He's
at a ברית, bris, so מזל טוב mazel tov to the family.
Today is December 5th, it's the 5th of כסלו. Kislev. Our דף
daf today is דף עין daf Ayin of בבא מציעא Bava Metzia
and we're going to start with the משנה mishna on ס"ט עמוד
ב'. Samech Tet Amud Bet. The last line, the first part of
the משנה mishna has already been discussed by the גמרא Gemara because
the way our משניות mishnayot are broken up and the way the
סוגיות sugyot are broken up with the גמרא Gemara is not exactly
always exactly aligned the way the printers decided to space them, so
sometimes the משנה mishna gets discussed before the משנה mishna actually comes
up on the page. So really we're just going to talk about
the last line of this משנה: mishna: ומפריז על שדהו ואינו חושש
משום ריבית. Umafriz al sadehhu ve'eino choshesh mishum ribbit. A person can
מפריז mafriz their field. That sounds like it means to inflate the
value. So how can you be allowed to inflate the value of
your field and that it's not going to be a problem of
ריבית? ribbit? So we're going to have to see, it's going to
involve some kind of a rental agreement about the field as the
גמרא'ס Gemara's first question. תנו רבנן: Tnu rabanan: So the rabbis bring
a ברייתא baraita that is the גמרא Gemara brings us a ברייתא
baraita to further expand on this idea of מפריז על שדהו. mafriz
al sadehhu. מפריז על שדהו ואינו חושש משום ריבית, Mafriz al sadehhu
ve'eino choshesh mishum ribbit, and it's no concern of ריבית. ribbit. כיצד?
Keitzad? What case is that? השוכר את השדה מחברו בעשרה כורין חטין
לשנה. Hasocher et hasadeh mechaveiro be'asara korin chittin leshana. A person rents
a field with the rental agreement being that he's going to pay
back the value of ten כור kor of wheat every year. That's
how much the rental value is. ואומר לו: Ve'omer lo: תן לי
מאתים זוז ואפרסנה. ten li matayim zuz ve'afarsena. And then he says
to the owner of the
field: Give me 200 זוז zuz and I'm going to invest that
into improving the quality of the field. ואני אעלה לך שנים עשר
כורין לשנה. Va'ani a'aleh lecha shneim asar korin leshana. And I'm going
to increase the rental value now to 12 כור kor of wheat
per year. מותר. Muttar. That's permissible. אבל אין מפריז לא על חנות
ולא על ספינה. Aval ein mafriz lo al chanut velo al sefina.
But you're not allowed to do that for a shop or a
boat. So the reason why presumably is because with a field, the
investment is actually going into some improvement which is going to increase
the value, the output of the field. That is whatever that investment
of 200 זוז zuz is going to be, you're going to get
better irrigation, you're going to get better fertilizers, things like that, that's
going to improve the output of the field. So if it improves
the output of the field in a tangible way, it's not a
kind of a ריבית ribbit suggestion because you actually are paying back
what was invested in in-kind. ואמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה:
Ve'amar Rav Nachman amar Rabba bar Avuha: פעמים שמפריז על חנות לצור
בצורה. Pe'amim shemafriz al chanut letzur batzura. But sometimes
you're allowed to do this מפריז, mafriz, you're allowed to inflate the
value, that is, for a shop to put up new illustrations, new
murals in the shop. ספינה לעשות בה אסקריא, Sefina la'asot bah iskarya,
or a boat to put up a new mast. So why? חנות
לצור בצורה דצבו בה אינשי והוי אגרא טפי. Chanut letzur batzura detzavu
bah inshei vehavei agra tfei. To put up a mural in your
shop because people are going to come by your store more if
it's more
attractive and there's going to be more business for the shop. ספינה
לעשות בה אסקריא כיון דשפירא אסקריא טפי אגרא דספינתא. Sefina la'asot bah
iskarya keivan deshapira iskarya tfei agra desfinata.
So and if you improve the quality of the ship by building
a new mast and you're going to be able to carry more
goods and it's going to actually create more profit, so that's the
same kind of מפריז. mafriz. That is, there are two different kinds
of investments you can make in improving either the store, the shop,
the ship, or a field. There are kinds of investments that actually
will make a return that's proportional and then that's not ריבית ribbit
problem because that's an investment that the owner has made that's going
to actually increase output. Compared to something where it's just aesthetic improvement
but it's not going to have a real impact on the business,
then that would be more of a ריבית ribbit problem because then
you're asking him to pay a higher rental fee without actually increasing
the amount of profit that the business agreement is getting.
דשפירא אסקריא טפי אגרא דספינתא. Deshapira iskarya tfei agra desfinata. So, ספינתא.
sfinata. So regarding
a boat, what does it say? אמר רב: Amar Rav: אגרא ופגרא.
Agra ufragra. When you rent a boat, רב Rav says you have
to pay the rental fee and you have to pay the value
of the depreciation, that is damage caused to the boat.
אמרו ליה רב כהנא ורב אסי לרב: Amru lei Rav Kahana veRav
Assi leRav: אי אגרא לא פגרא, Ei agra lo fagra, if you
pay a rental fee you shouldn't have to pay the depreciation. אי
פגרא לא אגרא, Ei fagra lo agra, and if you have to
pay a depreciation you shouldn't have to pay the rental fee. It's
either going to be one or the other. That's what רב אסי
Rav Assi and רב כהנא Rav Kahana said. שתיק רב. Shatik Rav.
רב Rav didn't have an answer to that. That is, רב Rav
had his opinion, but they asked him a pretty good question. אמר
רב ששת, Amar Rav Sheshet, a later אמורא Amora generations later, so
says: מאי טעמא שתיק רב? Mai ta'ama shatik Rav? Why was רב
Rav silent? Well maybe there was not a good record of what
רב Rav had said back, maybe that's the alternative.
Okay. But מאי טעמא שתיק רב? mai ta'ama shatik Rav? Why was
רב Rav silent? לא שמיע ליה הדיתניא: Lo shmieh lei hadatanya: Did
רב Rav not know this ברייתא? baraita? אף על פי שאמרו אין
מקבלין צאן ברזל מישראל. Af al pi she'amru ein mikablin tzon barzel
miyisrael. So even though they said you cannot receive צאן ברזל. tzon
barzel. צאן ברזל Tzon barzel we know is a kind of agreement
though it's going to be debated coming up in our next משנה
mishna on the top of עמוד ב'. amud bet. Basically the agreement
is that only one of the two partners carries the risk in
the investment. That is, one partner brings in the entire investment, the
other one does all the work, and then the initial investment is
fully guaranteed to be paid back at the end. That's why it's
applied to the case of a כתובה ketubah where the woman brings
in certain assets into the marriage. They're signed over to the husband
to have full ownership of throughout the marriage, but in the case
of divorce or divorce or if the husband predeceases his wife, then
that entire value is guaranteed to go back to the wife. That's
called צאן ברזל. tzon barzel. So ברזל barzel because it's very sure,
very sure kind of protected investment. So the ברייתא beraita says, אף
על פי שאמרו אין מקבלין צאן ברזל מישראל af al pi she'amru
ein mekablin tzon barzel mi'Yisrael אבל מקבלין צאן ברזל מן הנוכרים, aval
mekablin tzon barzel min ha'nochrim, so even though they said you cannot
accept צאן ברזל tzon barzel from a Jew, but you can accept
צאן ברזל tzon barzel from נוכרים, nochrim, that is because presumably because
of a problem of ריבית. ribit. אבל אמרו aval amru but they
said השם פרה לחבירו ha'sham parah le'chavero one who assesses the value
of the cow for his friend's cow ואמר לו ve'amar lo הרי
פרתך עשויה עלי בשלושים דינר, harei paratcha asuya alai be'shloshim dinar, so
he's renting the cow and he says I accept upon myself the
value of the cow as 30 dinars ואני אעלה לך ve'ani a'aleh
lecha סלע בחודש sela be'chodesh and I'm also going to pay you
one סלע sela every month, that is it sounds like there's a
guaranteed value for the cow based on if it were damaged and
there's a rental price, sounds like a good support for רב, Rav,
okay, מותר mutar but that would be permissible and therefore it sounds
like רב's Rav's case with the boat would also be permissible if
משום דלא שויא דמים ולא
עשה
mishum de'la shavya damim ve'lo
asah because presumably what's going to be the defense is because he
didn't actually pay the money at that point, the cow is not
being priced at 30 now, the price of 30 דינר dinar for
the cow is only if the cow were to die, okay, so
אמר רב ששת amar Rav Sheshet לא עשה דמים מחיים, lo asa
damim mechayim, the reason why is because he didn't actually turn the
cow into cash while it was alive, that is the assessment of
the cow's value was only if the cow would die אלא לאחר
מיתה, ela le'achar mitah, so אמר רב פפא amar Rav Papa so
רב פפא Rav Papa much later says הלכתא ספינה אגרא ופגרא, hilchata
sfina agra u'fagra, so רב פפא Rav Papa says paskens like רב,
Rav, that is against רב אסי Rav Assi and רב כהנא, Rav
Kahana, that is he felt that רב ששת'ס Rav Sheshet's defense of
רב Rav from this ברייתא beraita was sufficient, so he says הלכתא
ספינה אגרא ופגרא, hilchata sfina agra u'fagra, that with the boat you
can charge both the rental price as well as the depreciation ונהגו
בני כופרא אגרא בשעת משיכה פגרא בשעת שבירה ve'nahagu benei Kufra agra
be'sha'at meshicha fagra be'sha'at shevira and the custom of the sailors or
perhaps people from Cyprus or maybe there's a different translation בני כופרא
benei Kufra perhaps literally people who use pitch because sailors smear pitch
on the boats, we know that from פרשת נח Parshat Noach that
to protect the wood and to keep the water out,
so the custom of the sailors was to pay the rental price
at the beginning בשעת משיכה be'sha'at meshicha when you gain control of
the boat ופגרא בשעת שבירה u'fagra be'sha'at shevira and they would only
pay the price for the depreciation once it broke. Now does that
mean the assessment of the value for the damage is at the
time of the breakage? Does it mean the payment is only scheduled
for the time of the breakage? It's a bit of a מחלוקת
ראשונים, machloket Rishonim,
but so it seems like part of the reason they would divide
it into two payments is to make it seem less like ריבית.
ribit. That is, ריבית ribit seems like well if I borrow it
now and then I'm going to pay you back a larger value
later, that's going to be more of a ריבית ribit problem. But
if you pay a little bit now and a little bit later,
it'll look more like it's clearly two different payments, one is for
the rental and one is for the damage, okay, so אטו במנהגא
תליא מילתא atu be'minhaga talya milta because we saw in the משנה
mishna that this entire discussion is all about מקום שנהגו, makom she'nahagu,
at least if you parse the משנה mishna a certain way, that
is at least the previous clause in the משנה mishna was about
מנהג, minhag, the גמרא Gemara asserts as well that this whole discussion
about the מפריז על שדהו mafriz al sadehu question is also going
to be about מנהג minhag and if it's about מנהג minhag then
there's some flexibility about what people would do, that is it goes
by the customs of the marketplace. We know that many things in
בהלכה ba'halacha especially if you read the רמב"ם Rambam in many of
his הלכות halachot about commercial הלכות, halachot, many times he just goes
through he says and he says כל תנאי שבממון קיים kol tnai
she'bemamon kayam like any agreement that you make monetary values unless you're
violating certain מצוות mitzvot obviously, but generally if you make certain agreements,
the agreement is binding. So that's the kind of point about מנהג,
minhag, you go by the customs of, you know, מנהג השוק, minhag
ha'shuk, okay, אמשום דמדי דתני מנהגא a'mishum de'madi de'tani minhaga because the
משנה mishna had mentioned מנהג. minhag. אמר רב ענן אמר שמואל, amar
Rav Anan amar Shmuel, next question. The question is going to be
about orphans. So how do we deal with orphans? So אמר רב
ענן אמר שמואל, amar Rav Anan amar Shmuel, רב ענן Rav Anan
quoted from שמואל, Shmuel, מעות של יתומים מותר להלוותם בריבית. ma'ot shel
yetomim mutar le'halvotam be'ribit. Wow,
the money of orphans you can lend them out with interest. That's
a big question. So the first question we have to ask is
what kind of interest are we talking about? Some of the ראשונים
Rishonim certainly seem to
think this would be
אבק ריבית avak ribit probably, דרבנן, de'rabbanan, so many of the ראשונים
Rishonim take it not to mean. any kind of ריבית ribbit. *ribit*,
however I think it was the ריטב"א Ritva. *Ritva* quotes at least
one opinion says you could charge any kind of ריבית ribbit *ribit*
you want at all, even totally a hundred percent ריבית ribbit, דאורייתא
Deoraisa *ribit d'oraisa* for יתומים yetomim. *yesomim*.
Well let's look at תוספות *Tosfos*. תוספות *Tosfos* pointed out points out
in the last line of the first תוספות *Tosfos*, תידמי *tidami*, קסבר
*ksavar* דלאו *de'lav* מיחייב *mechayiv* לוה *love* משום *mishum* לא lo, תשיך
*lo tashi'ech* אלא *ela* כשגם *keshegam* המלוה *hamalve* מוזהר *muzhar*. So if
we're talking about יתומים yetomim, *yesomim*, we're talking about orphans who are
below the age of מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*, well at that age they're
not oblig- they don't have the requirement the obligation to keep the
laws of ריבית ribbis *ribit*.
But presumably it's the בית דין beis din, *beis din* that's
doing this not the יתום *yosom* himself. So that becomes a question
of how does the function of the אפוטרופוס *apotropos* work, that is
when you have an אפוטרופוס *apotropos* making a financial agreement for a
minor, does that count as if the minor is doing it him
or herself or does it count as if the אפוטרופוס *apotropos* is
doing it.
If it's the case the אפוטרופוס *apotropos* only is doing it.
You're saying obviously
but if I'm doing it on behalf of the minor I'm the
one
that's killing, don't do אין שליח לדבר עבירה *ein shaliach l'devar aveira*.
But this is the בית דין Beis Din *beis din* is doing
it. But is it about שליחות *shlichus* or is it about what's
happening with the money. I'm just telling you what the אמוראים Amoraim
*Amoraim* said. שמואל Shmuel, *Shmuel* sounds like he says מעות של יתומים
yetomim מותר להלוותם בריבית *maos shel yesomim mutar lehalvosam beribis*. You're allowed
to lend them with interest and obviously many of the ראשונים Rishonim
*Rishonim* take that to only mean דרבנן *d'rabanan* interest, but the opinion
that it's דאורייתא *d'oraisa* is even quoted in שלחן ערוך *Shulchan Aruch*
as a minority opinion. So just so you should know both opinions.
אמר ליה אימא ליה ליהוי הכי *amar lei eima lei lehavy hachi*.
Okay so you have to take it up with שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel*.
Is there opinion that the יתומים yetomim, *yesomim* themselves?
Well so the יתומים yetomim? *yesomim* themselves can't be doing it only
because they're too young. They're too young. The question is how young
is young? We're going to come to that in a question.
But yeah if we're just going back to ריבית ribbis. *ribit* people
make all kinds of adjustments to put their money into account for
their kids and then you're responsible for it and then they can
use it to profit from interest.
Well but so it has to be יתומים yetomim, *yesomim* remember the
parents have to have died.
Well I mean why if we're just going by their age?
But here it's also because they're יתומים yetomim? *yesomim*. We make certain
allowances to provide for the financial protection of יתומים yetomim *yesomim*.
Like the value that's being adjusted here as you're saying it's so
important to make sure that they do have enough money that we're
going to ease down on the ריבית ribbis, *ribit*.
Right so that would defend the position that it's only about ריבית
דרבנן ribbit d'rabbanan *ribit d'rabanan*, that is we would relax the rabbinic
requirements for the sake of, but that becomes a question. So obviously
that's the question.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* so you'll have to let me get
to the next line of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* because the next
line of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, אמר ליה רב Rav... נחמן *amar
lei Rav Nachman* משום דיתמי נינהו *mishum de'yasmei ninhu* ספינן להו איסורא
*safinan lehu issura* just because they're orphans are we allowed them to
consume something that's אסור assur *assur*? And we know the general principle
is קטן katan. אוכל נבילות Neveilos, בית דין Beis Din מוזהרין לו
*katan ochel neveilos beis din muzarin lo*, if it's a child is
breaking breaking מצוות mitzvot, *mitzvos* the the community the בית דין din
*beis din* has a requirement to step in and intervene. Okay. Is
that true?
I thought that was a מחלוקת Machlokes *machlokes*?
It becomes a מחלוקת machlokes *machlokes* about which kinds of איסורים *issurim*,
how does it exactly whole סוגיה *sugya* in יומא *Yoma* about which
kinds of איסורים *issurim* and is it איסורי חפצא *issurei heftza* and
איסורי גברא *issurei gavra* and all sorts of things it becomes a
whole big question in למדות *lamdus* it's a fun סוגיה *sugya*. Anyway
so but the main point here so
יתמי דאכלי דלאו דידהו *yatmei d'achlei d'lav did'hu* if they're יתומים yetomim
*yesomim* who profit from something which is not theirs, ליזלו בתר שבקייהו
*lizlu basar shavkaihu* they're going to follow those who came before them,
they're going to follow their parents to the grave basically. So that's
a pretty harsh curse. Now does that mean it's אסור *assur* or
does that just mean it's bad but it's permissible? That's also an
interesting question. רב נחמן *Rav Nachman* is certainly upset about this kind
of permission, but it's not necessarily clear that he's saying it's not
permissible. אמר ליה *amar lei* so אימא לי *eima li* איזו גופא
דעובדא היכי *izu gufa de'uvda heichi* so what case are we talking
about? היכי הוה *heichi hava*? אמר ליה *amar lei* ההוא דודא דבני
מר עוקבא דהוה בי מר שמואל Shmuel *hahu duda d'vnei Mar Ukva
de'hava bei Mar Shmuel*. So what was the case? The case is
talking about there was a דודא *duda*, there was a large cauldron
that was that belonged to the children of מר עוקבא *Mar Ukva*,
presumably מר עוקבא *Mar Ukva* had already died so they were יתומים
yetomim. *yesomim* and his wife had died as well דהוה בי מר
שמואל Shmuel *de'hava bei Mar Shmuel*, it was at מר שמואל *Mar
Shmuel* house and מר שמואל *Mar Shmuel* presumably was renting out this
giant cauldron for other people to use and the money would go
to benefit the יתומים yetomim *yesomim*. So תקיל ויהיב ליה *takil v'yahiv
lei*, תקיל ושקיל ליה ve-shakil lei, *takil v'shakil lei*. He would weigh
it and give it out, he would weigh it and take it
back, that is every time it changed hands he would weigh the
pot. Why? So שקיל אגרא ושקיל פחתא *shakil agra v'shakil pachta* he
would take a rental fee and he would take the amount for
the weight of the pot that had decreased, that is if certain
amount of the metal had come had burned off or had corroded
in some way then he would charge people for that depreciation as
well. So אי אגרא לא פחתא *ei agra lo pachta* if he
should charge a rental fee he shouldn't be able to charge a
depreciation. ואי פחתא לא אגרא *v'ei pachta lo agra* and if he
charges the depreciation he shouldn't be allowed to charge a rental fee
because that's like ריבית ribis. *ribit*. A proof that for the sake
of יתומים yetomim *yesomim* you can charge ריבית ribis *ribit*, at least
some kind of ריבית דרבנן ribbit d'rabbanan. *ribit d'rabanan*.
Isn't that the custom in that case I guess?
Presumably something like that. But again this is about the pot case
not about the boat case. The boat case is more like a
field where they would be permissible because it's an investment into the
return that the ship is going to make more money or something
like that. Here the pot is not going to make any more
money.
Why is depreciation, I don't think I'm getting clearly why depreciation cost
is like ריבית? ribis. In other words, like I'm renting your pot,
but then if it's depreciated because some of the metal has worn
off, effectively I bought that metal. I've used it.
Well but so that's part of the question. That is, if I
lend you my pot and then you pay me back the pot,
and then you paid me money to borrow it, so that's like
the rental agreement. I own something and you're allowed to use it
because you paid me. But then, if you're also going to charge
for the depreciation, it's kind of like a different mode. Not upfront.
Right. It becomes more the issue again, right? Right. One is like
did you buy it and then you're giving it back and then
if it depreciated then you should pay the difference? That is one
option. And one is like is it borrowing, but if it's borrowing
then you should just give back the item, you shouldn't have to
pay the depreciation. You can say הרי שלך לפניך harei shelcha lefanecha
sort of thing.
But it's the same thing, is it structured as a sale or
is it structured as a loan?
And when that's over, because the way loans and sales operate are
always at odds with each other. They're different kinds of transactions. So
then when you kind of combine the two together, that's when you
get ריבית. ribis Great question though, Ash. That is, well and ריבית
ribis in general is, I'm paying you for the right to borrow
money from you and pay it back, right? So that's the whole,
that's the core problem of ריבית, Ribbit which is like a sale
and a loan together. So really I guess that's a great way
of summarizing it.
Okay, so then
the התשב"ץ HaTashbetz says it's all kinds of interest.
If you just hear... Okay, so the example in the גמרא Gemara
is a ריבית דרבנן ribis de-rabbanan case, so it's certainly a good
proof. I'm just telling you there are ראשונים Rishonim who disagree with
you. Oh, so go study the ריטב"א. Ritva Okay. The גמרא Gemara
itself is,
the
גמרא Gemara, itself at least only quotes a case which was ריבית
Ribbit דרבנן. Okay. Fine.
Well all we have to know is the ריטב"א's are very smart.
Okay. Okay. Okay.
I'm not smart, so like, but it seems to me pretty black
and white what the גמרא's Gemara trying to do here.
So the גמרא Gemara says back, so that is רב... it's שמואל,
right? So it's רב ענאן Rav Annan quoting שמואל says back, אמר
ליה כי הא אפילו בדידקנני נמי שרי למיעבד. amar lei ki ha
afilu bididkanani nami shari lemeivad. So this, that thing with the pot,
that would be permissible even for people with beards, that is even
for adult men to be performing that transaction. That is, don't say
that that's a special קולא, kula, special leniency we're employing for the
יתומים. Yesomim, Why? דהא מקבלי עלייהו חוסכא דנחשא דכמה דמיקלי נחשא בציר
דמיה. deha mekablei aleihu chuska denachsha dechama demeklei nachsha batsir damei. Because
in that case, there is actually a corrosion of the copper. Why?
Because when you use a copper pot over the fire, it's going
to corrode more and that metal is going to actually decrease over
time. דכמה דמיקלי נחשא בציר דמיה dechama demeklei nachsha batsir damei because
every time you use the copper pot, the price, the value of
the pot is going to go down. And that's why in that
case, because the depreciation is so measurable, it's an appreciable depreciation.
And so because the price is very obviously going down and you
could measure it, he could weigh it each time and see how
much it had gone down, that's why this would be permissible even
for adults. Now interestingly, why does it say it says דקנני, dekanani,
people with beards? That is not just reaching the age of מצוות,
which is 12 or 13, but actually people who've reached maturity in
a more social sense. So it's interesting to note the question, how
does it apply to יתומים, Yesomim? orphans? The principle גדול הסומך על
שולחן אביו נקרא קטן. gadol hasomech al shulchan aviv nikra katan. Sorry...
גדול הסומך על שולחן אביו נקרא קטן, gadol hasomech al shulchan aviv
nikra katan,
that even an adult child who is relying on their parents, a
dependent on their parents, for certain financial הלכות halachot is still considered
to be a קטן. That is even going up until nowadays, even
up to 26, you know, we have the health insurance and things
like that. Certainly people in college are dependent on their parents often.
So in that case, you would for financial matters consider them קטנים.
ketanim. They would fall into this kind of arrangement. So it's an
interesting question and there's a cute story about the וילנא גאון. Vilna
Gaon. The וילנא גאון Vilna Gaon came across a guy with a
חומש Chumash and written in his חומש Chumash for his grandfather was
an abbreviation that nobody could understand about the פסוק pasuk את המאור
הגדול לממשלת היום ואת המאור הקטן לממשלת הלילה. et hamaor hagadol lemshelet
hayom ve'et hamaor hakatan lemshelet halaila. The sun is the מאור הגדול
maor hagadol and the moon is מאור הקטן. maor hakatan.
And why, so he had this strange abbreviation and the וילנא גאון
Vilna Gaon was able to see the abbreviation and poof, instantly said
the abbreviation was גדול הסומך על שולחן אביו נקרא קטן. gadol hasomech
al shulchan aviv nikra katan. Why? Because the moon, even though it
provides a lot of light, even though it's very large, it gets
its light from the sun. And since the light from the sun
is reflected off of the moon, which they already knew at the
time of the וילנא גאון, Vilna Gaon, so then they were able
to call the moon מאור הקטן maor hakatan because it gets its
light from the sun. Okay.
Is this דקנני dekanani the same source as כנעני Kena'ani of the
Canaanites? Which
כנעני?
Kenani? No. What word? The beard? Oh,
דקנני, Diknani, דקן, dakan, like a דקנני... diknani... yeah, קוף. kuf.
Right, the beard, because the beard, so there are ראשונים Rishonim who
say the cutoff point is whether or not the יתומים Yesomim have
beards. That is not the... older than 13. Exactly. Older than בר
מצוה. bar mitzvah. Okay.
At least that would presumably contrast the adult with the...
Okay, but you would say גדולים. gedolim. Why דקנני? Diknani? דקנני Diknani
is a strange... Okay. Look, so you don't have to take that
דיוק. diyuk. Okay. ואמר רבה בר שילה אמר רב חסדא, Ve'amar Rabba
bar Shila amar Rav Chisda, ואמרי לה, ve'amri lah, אמר רבה בר
יוסף בר חמה אמר רב
ששת. amar Rabba bar Yosef bar Chama amar Rav Sheshet. So we
have two different traditions who said this, but what did they say?
מעות של יתומים מותר להלוותן קרוב לשכר ורחוק להפסד. Ma'osh shel yetomim
mutar lehalvosan karov liskhar verakhok lehefsed. So another permission for יתומים, Yesomim
the permission to lend the money or to invest the money of
orphans in a case which is קרוב לשכר, karov liskhar, it's easy
to get a profit, ורחוק להפסד, verakhok lehefsed, and low risk. Okay.
So now we're going to have to see why would we have
thought otherwise. We would think any investment that is high profit and
low risk is the best kind of investment. We're going to see...
We had this before.
Okay, so we'll see the ברייתא. braisa. The ברייתא braisa says תנו
רבנן. Tanu rabbanan. קרוב לשכר ורחוק להפסד, Karov liskhar urakhok lehefsed, if
there's a case which is easy to make a profit and difficult
to... it's a low risk, רשע. rasha. That is if you enter
into such an agreement on those terms, you're a רשע, rasha, because
why? Because your other business partner is going to get the short
end of the stick. They're going to carry all the risk. So
that's bad. קרוב להפסד ורחוק לשכר, Karov lehefsed verakhok liskhar, but if
you take it the opposite, that it's easy... high risk and a
low payoff, that's a חסיד. chasid. That's a righteous person.
Then you wonder why they're poor.
Well okay, but we're going to see. So I'm going to ask
a question on that one second. But that's a חסיד, chasid, that's
someone who's taking extra special care to avoid ריבית Ribbit on their
own, so they try to take a higher risk and a lower
payoff in order to avoid ריבית. Ribbit. קרוב לזה ולזה רחוק מזה
ומזה זו מידת כל אדם. Karov lazeh velazeh rakhok mizeh umizeh zo
midas kol adam. Most people will take high risk, high gain, or
low risk, low gain, that's a normal investment. That is when you
get into this business partnership, most people share it equitably. Okay. So
obviously if there's going to be a חסיד, chasid, it turns the
other person into a רשע, rasha, which is also interesting. What Michael
said about why, you know, are rabbis supposed to make bad investments,
we remember back in דף מ Daf Mem
that רב יהודה Rav Yehuda criticized שמואל for... no the opposite, the
גמרא, Gemara the סתם stam voice of the גמרא Gemara quotes an
opinion of שמואל to criticize רב יהודה Rav Yehuda for making what
seemed like a bad business decision. So in fact many of the
אמוראים also are kind of pushing to make sure they make good
investments as well, so we have some of that...
No, but it's funny, I mean, because you know, they say that,
but like you know, but then on the other hand, the rabbis
get you know, the right to bring their stuff to market first,
like you know...
Okay, so they get certain privileges as well. Okay, okay. So they
have to keep it in balance. You know, if you have a
privilege, you also have to make sure to weigh it against so
it doesn't get abused. That becomes a whole question. So חסיד, chasid,
right? מילי דנזיקין Milei dinizikin you have to study to be a
חסיד, chasid, right, according to one opinion. So מילי דנזיקין, Milei dinizikin,
the best way to be a real חסיד chasid is to try
to avoid... avoid
stealing from other people, avoid charging ריבית, Ribbit all sorts of kind
of things that you can get yourself involved in in just trying
to make a living, but it can be very difficult. Okay. אמר
ליה רבה לרב יוסף הני זוזי דיתומים היכי עבדינן להו? Amar lei
Rabba le-Rav Yosef hani zuz d'yetomim heikhi avdinan lehu?
So what are we supposed to do with the money of יתומים?
Yesomim That is, what kind of investment would you say is קרוב
לשכר ורחוק להפסד? karov liskhar verakhok lehefsed? That is, something which is
normally called a רשע, rasha, a case... you know, a wicked person
would do that, that's been permitted for יתומים, Yesomim for orphans. So
what case would you do? אמר ליה מותבינן להו בי
דינא ויהבינן להו זוזא זוזא, Amar lei motbinan lehu be-be dina ve'yavinan
lehu zuzu zuzu, like pay it off זוזא זוזא, zuzu zuzu, coin
by coin. אמר ליה...
I'm sorry what's this? What are you doing?
It sounds like some kind of an annuity that you kind of
put the money in court and the court can dish it out
over time, which doesn't sound like very much of an investment. Okay,
so that's a low risk kind of a case, right? That's like
putting it in the bank as if. Okay.
But who's the other side of the transaction who's a loser?
Right now here it's just יתומים. That's why it doesn't seem to
make sense. Okay. So אמר ליה והא קא כליה קרנא, Amar lei
veha ka-kalya karna, but then doesn't the principal part of the investment
depreciate? That is it's not an investment. That's just like putting it
in the bank and taking it back out again. אמר ליה מר
היכי עביד? Amar lei Mar heikhi avid? So he said to him
back fine, so what would you do? אמר ליה בדקינן גברא דאית
ליה דהבא פריכא, Amar lei badkinan gavra de'it lei dehava perikha,
I would find a person who has pieces of gold, like gold
nuggets, not somebody with gold coins, interestingly, gold nuggets, ונקטינן דהבא מיניה,
venaktinan dehava minei, and I would take the gold from him, ויהבינן
להו ניהליה, ve'yavinan lehu nihaleih, and I would pay it back to
him, קרוב לשכר ורחוק להפסד. karov liskhar verakhok lehefsed. And that would
be a case which is in a case where it is easy
to make a profit and a low risk. I'm not understanding. What's
the...
So look what רש"י Rashi says: דהבא פריכא, Dehava perikha, גרוטות של
זהב דודאי שלהן, grutot shel zahav devadai shelahen,
because they're gold nuggets we can presume they're not borrowed from someone
else. What's the risk? The risk is that
if
you
exchange... not be coinage, something that could have been borrowed from someone
else, but actually belongs to the person. So that's why, okay, because
people don't give that as a
פיקדון, pikadon, okay, בכיון דעשיר הוא, bekivan de-ashir hu, and since he
has a lot of gold, he's very rich, יש לו לגבות ממנו
אם יאבדו מעותיו, yesh lo ligabot mimenu im yavdu ma'otav, so then
if he loses the money he'll still be able to pay it
back, so that's why it's a low risk kind of investment.
I'm not sure. So wait, see we're not really saying you're doing
something that looks shady. You're just giving it to a very good
businessman. Is that what we're saying?
Something like that. You're giving it to someone who is reliable. Reliable
in that his business is something which you know is not borrowed
from someone else, so there's no liens on his property, and someone
who'll be able to invest it in an appropriate way.
So we've totally walked this back from before where we thought we
were, we said it was אסור to do ריבית. Ribbit.
So the previous, right, the previous סוגיא sugya was about can you
charge ריבית Ribbit. for יתומים? The answer was yes, and the question
was what kind of ריבית. Ribbit The second case was you're allowed
to do a case of קרוב לשכר ורחוק להפסד, karov lisechar verachok
lehefsed, which normally would be unfair or not recommended or would make
you a רשע. rasha. Why is it not recommended? It's not recommended
because you're kind of exploiting the other party in your business deal.
In this case, that exploitation going from the orphans to a wealthy,
wealthy businessman, that would be an appropriate kind of exploitation.
Is there exploitation? I'm sorry. קרוב לשכר ורחוק להפסד karov lisechar verachok
lehefsed in this case would be what they used, what was, somebody
if you bought it from somebody who it wasn't clear that it
could have been his, more chance that it'd be a פיקדון. pikadon.
If, right, so if it was someone who there was a chance
that it would be, exactly. That would be a concern.
Why would we advise רב אשי? Rav Ashi?
I don't get it. Because we want to make sure that the
יתומים have their money invested in a way that's going to be
positive, it's going to be a good investment. Right.
I don't understand the חסיד chasid part.
So חסיד chasid just means normally, well not necessarily that kind of
a case, but in general, in general, מידת חסידות midas chasidus is
to do what? Is to pick an investment which generally has a
lower payout and a higher level of risk so that you're not
exploiting the other party. That is, the other party will carry less
risk and the other party will carry a little bit more return,
and that guarantees that you make sure that you're not doing anything
wrong. It makes the other person certainly seem like they're cheating you.
The wrong thing would just be that you might be exploiting them,
that's what you're saying?
Exactly. So in this case, the case that's allowed is יתומים as
if exploiting a generous benefactor. That is, this guy who has all
the gold pieces, he's someone who can afford to be exploited.
It's real estate, you can buy a property really low and then
flip it. Right. And if it's just a חסיד, chasid, don't try
to find people who,
well, in a case like that could also be,
right, try to find somebody who is selling at a normal price.
Right, something like that. Make sure that the risk, the risk and
the payout are equitable, which is generally a good recommendation. Yeah.
This was a confusion in the previous case was that it's not
actually ריבית ribbis that the orphans are taking, because that example you
said,
the example in the גמרא Gemara was a ריבית ribbis. דרבנן case.
Or maybe not even. That is, the case that was given as
an example may not have even been ריבית ribbis. at all, therefore
you'll need a different example to explain what, what case would be
allowed to charge the interest. Okay. קרוב לשכר ורחוק להפסד. karov lisechar
verachok lehefsed. Okay. ונסבינה דהוה מיניה, venasina de-hava minei, they take the
gold from him, ויהבינו להו ניהליה, ve-yahavinu lehu nihalei, קרוב לשכר ורחוק
להפסד. karov lisechar verachok lehefsed. אבל דבר מסוים, aval davar mesuyam, but
something which has sort of come into its form precise, like gold
coins, לא, no. דילמא פקדון נינהו, dilma pikadon inhu, maybe it's a
פיקדון. pikadon. If it's a פיקדון, pikadon, then the owner is going
to come claim it and it's going to be a loss for
the יתומים. ואתי מריה יהיב סימנים, ve-asi mari ye-hava simanim,
the owner will come with סימנים, simanim, ושקיל ליה, and he'll take
it. אמר רב אשי, amar Rav Ashi, תינח, teinach, אי משתכח גברא
דאית ליה דהבא פריכא, ei mishtakach gavra de-is lei de-hava paricha, fine,
I'll give you the case that you find somebody who is this
kind of a wealthy investor who has gold nuggets where he's able
to, you know, all of those qualifications that you need in order
to make this deal. אי לא משתכח גברא דאית ליה דהבא פריכא,
ei lo mishtakach gavra de-is lei de-hava paricha, ניכלו זוזי דיתמי? nichlu
zuzei de-yasmei? Are you going to tell me that if you can't
find such a person, that the יתומים's property should just get consumed
and totally spent out? אלא אמר רב אשי, ela amar Rav Ashi,
what did רב אשי Rav Ashi say? חזינן גברא דמשפו נכסיה, chazinan
gavra de-meshafu nachsei, you find someone who's doing well in business in
general, ומהימן, u-meheman, and is a reliable, trustworthy person, ושמע דינא דאורייתא,
ve-shama dina de-Oraisa, and he follows the laws of the תורה, Torah,
ולא מקבל שמתא דרבנן, ve-lo mekabbel shamta de-rabbanan,
and he's never been put into שמתא shamta by the רבנן, rabbanan,
ויהבינו להו ניהליה ve-yahavinu lehu nihalei בבי דינא, be-vei dina, and you
give it to him in court. Now, what does doing it in
court mean? That's a good question. So רש"י Rashi says it has
to do with הפקר בית דין הפקר, hefker beis din hefker, that
in order to guarantee that the יתומים will get a good deal,
the court can impose הפקר בית דין הפקר hefker beis din hefker
to redistribute the property. But some of the other ראשונים Rishonim don't
like that and suggest alternative reasons for why it would need to
be done in בית דין, perhaps in order to appoint the אפיטרופוס
apotropus for this case, perhaps just in order to be able to
fairly judge the case. Different possibilities. Yes.
What does it if they don't do If we don't take any
action because that's gonna involve these יתומים, why is that the case?
Why is it... why is inaction because of the יתומים?
Because think about it, the יתומים have living expenses and the יתומים
have an estate. So the estate, leave it alone, so leave it
alone, they're going to end up consuming that money over time. They
have to spend it to buy food or to pay their rent
or anything else. So if you just have money in the bank,
you're going to end up running out of money. The way to
support yourself, to enable them to be well-supported, is to find an
investment that's actually going to make money and that they'll be able
to live off of the profits and be able to maintain their
lifestyle accordingly. So that's the important difference. And that's I mean חזל
Chazal already, even in the time of חזל, Chazal, you know we
think חזל Chazal had a very primitive understanding of economics and certainly
in many ways they did, it was before there were all sorts
of developments that we have now, but the general understanding that investments
are a much better choice than keeping your money in the bank
is certainly obvious to anyone trying to learn these סוגיות. Sogyos. That
putting your money in the bank, well the money's going to run
out. But having an investment that has a payoff is something beneficial.
The question is then how to do it appropriately such that there's
no ריבית and things like that.
Yeah, so I'm the one with the more primitive,
like I would have thought that זוזא זוזא, Zuza Zuza, like a
type of annuity payment out to the יתומים would be a good
thing, it would be stable, the money would be there, they could...
It's not
invested, it'll just run out.
Meaning you just give it to them and you just give it
to... they take it from them and then give it back to
them over the course of time. Right, like the bank.
All it does is it gives them every month, they get their
check an allowance for the month, but there's no growth. The money
could be better used as seed money, but how without a ריבית
problem? Exactly. So the special allowance then is that they're allowed to
take investments which are קרוב לשכר ורחוק להפסד. Karov Leschar Verachok Lehefsed.
They're allowed to take
inequitable, biased kinds of investments that allow them to benefit because they're
יתומים that we normally would not recommend. Low risk, high return.
Well yeah, the way they explained it here is that everyone... that
investment would be that
if
you go into the עיסקא Iska with somebody where the guy bears
all the loss but you still get some of the profit. Right.
So that would be one of these things.
Right. Which in the reverse would not be allowed. Right.
So it's so fascinating that the term היתר עיסקא Heter Iska hasn't
like come up in...
Well, היתר עיסקא Heter Iska is a whole... I mean, what we
refer to as היתר עיסקא Heter Iska is very much more modern
development about how to create a business agreement that basically allows charging
really real interest
in order to avoid ריבית problems.
So it's not a תלמודי Talmudi phrase?
As far as I know, no, but I'm not an expert in
this topic at all for sure. Let's turn the page and take
a look at the next משנה Mishna and see how far we
can get. I have to go in about 20 minutes, so I
just want to cut it short a little bit. The משנה Mishna
says: אין מקבלין צאן ברזל מישראל מפני שהוא ריבית. Ein Mekablin Tzon
Barzel Miyisrael Mipnei Shehu Ribbit. You're not allowed to do a case
of צאן ברזל Tzon Barzel with another Jewish person because that's ריבית.
Look in רש"י Rashi says: כל אחריות הנכסים על המקבל. Kol Achrayos
Hanichasim Al Hamikabel. The entire responsibility for the properties, for the investment,
is on the מקבל. Mikabel. That is, one investor gives all the
money, gives it to the other person and then that person has
to do all the work and then they're just going to pay
back at the end. That is, I give you $10,000 now, you
take that investment and go do something with it, and then ten...
a year later or whatever, you give me back $10,000. That would
be like a צאן ברזל Tzon Barzel kind of agreement, but that's
ריבית because basically... or you pay back with the benefit... sorry, you
would pay back with the return, with the profit, that would be
ריבית. I lent you money, you invested it, you gave me back
the profits, that's ריבית. Okay. אבל מקבלין צאן ברזל מן העכו"ם, Aval
Mekablin Tzon Barzel Min Ha'akum, but you can accept a צאן ברזל
Tzon Barzel type investment from a non-Jewish person. ולווין מהן ומלווין אותם
בריבית, Velovin Mehen Umalvin Osam Beribbit, and you can borrow from them
and lend to them with ריבית with real דאורייתא interest. וכן בגר
תושב, Vechen Beger Toshav, and also a גר תושב. Ger Toshav. גר
תושב Ger Toshav is an interesting question, who counts as a גר
תושב? Ger Toshav? We'll get to that in a minute. מלווה ישראל
מעותיו של עכו"ם מדעת העכו"ם, Malveh Yisrael Ma'osav Shel Akum Mida'as Ha'akum,
a Jewish person can
lend out the money of a non-Jew with his permission, אבל לא
מדעת ישראל, Aval Lo Mida'as Yisrael, but not with the permission of
an Israel. It's unclear what that case is, the גמרא's going to
get to it eventually in a next דף Daf or so. So
who's a גר תושב? Ger Toshav? גר תושב's Ger Toshav a big
מחלוקת in מסכת סנהדרין Masechet Sanhedrin about who counts as a גר
תושב. Ger Toshav. Seemingly רש"י's Rashi only qualifications seem to be a
person who does not do עבודה זרה Avoda Zara and nonetheless eats...
eats נבילות, neveilos? eats non-kosher meat. However, most of the other ראשונים
seem to think it has something to do with the מצוות בני
נח. Mitzvos Bnei Noach. And perhaps a גר תושב Ger Toshav seemingly
from the גמרא in בכורות Bechoros involves actually coming to בית דין
and accepting upon yourself to be a גר תושב. Ger Toshav. One
of the cases that comes up and one of the big questions
in conversion questions is there's a סוגיא Sogya that talks about a
person who comes to בית
דין לקבל דברי תורה חוץ מדבר אחד, Lekabel Divrei Torah Chutz Midavar
Echad, a person who wants to accept the laws of the Torah
except for one thing. And they said אין מקבלין אותו, ein mekabelin
oto, you can't accept such a person. Is that talking about a
person coming to convert to Judaism but because they don't want to
keep one מצוה mitzvah that counts as not allowed to convert? Or
is it talking about
is מקבל דברי תורה חוץ מדבר אחד, mekabel divrei Torah chutz midavar
echad, that is a person who's allowed, who's coming to accept all
the words of the Torah except for one thing, that is eating
נבילות? Well, maybe that's talking about accepting a גר תושב. ger toshav.
And the rule is nowadays we can't accept גר תושב ger toshav
because we don't have the יובל yovel year. So that's a big
מחלוקת in how to understand that סוגיא sugya in בכורות Bechoros with
major implications for understanding questions of conversion. Yeah.
This משנה mishna means I can't give you seed money, you go
then manufacture a product, you give me one of the products when
it's finished, but let's say that product is not worth as much
as what I've given you, so you've profited from that?
That's the opposite agreement. Exactly.
That's the opposite, that's not what's talked about in the משנה mishna
as far as I understand it. The case here, I mean, you
look in
רש"י. Rashi. רש"י Rashi says כל אחריות נכסים על המקבל kol acharayus
nechasim al hamekabel ושמתם עליה במעות veshamtam aleha bemaos וכל זמן שאינו
נותן לו מעותיה חולקין השכר. vekol zman she'eino nosein lo me'oseha cholkin
haschar. As long as he hasn't paid back the seed money, they
split the profit. That is, one person invests all the money, one
person does all the work, they split the profits, and then at
the end, the investor still gets their investment back also, they get
a lump sum of the seed money. That would be the צאן
ברזל tzon barzel probably.
They get all the seed money back plus...
Right. If we just entered into an agreement, I gave the seed
money, you did all the work, and that was our partnership, that
would be fine, because that's a partnership, that's building the business. But
because there's that lump sum payback of the initial seed money, that's
what makes it a ריבית problem, because then all of the profits
that were accumulated over time becomes ריבית. So the גמרא says to
explain this case, למימרא דברשותיה דמקבל קיימא. lemimra debershutei d'mekabel ka'ima. It's
obvious from the משנה mishna that the investment transfers to the מקבל,
mekabel, to the one who received the investment. Why? Because the whole
problem is that it's ריבית. That is, the investor gives the money
to the מקבל, mekabel, the מקבל mekabel does the business, pays back
money over time, and then pays back the money. But over time,
it meant it was in his control, it was his money. ורמינהו,
ureminhu, but it's contradicted by the ברייתא braisa in משנה mishna in
בכורות. Bechoros. המקבל צאן ברזל מן העובד כוכבים, hamekabel tzon barzel min
ha'akum, a person who accepts a צאן ברזל tzon barzel type of
agreement with a non-Jewish investor, ולדות פטורין מן הבכורה. vlados peturin min
habechora.
The offspring of those sheep are exempt from בכורה. bechora. That is,
a firstborn male sheep would normally have to become a קרבן korban
if they're owned by a Jew, but if they're owned by a
non-Jew, they're exempt, which is what we do nowadays to avoid having
a bunch of קרבנות korbanos running around. But the point is that
a non-Jewish investor, if the investor gave the seed money, the offspring
will be exempt from בכורה, bechora, that sounds like it belongs to
the investor, not that it belongs to the Jewish partner. So what
does אביי Abaye say?
In whose ownership
is the properties considered to be in the interim? So אמר אביי,
amar Abaye, אביי Abaye responds to resolve this contradiction between our משנה
mishna and the משנה mishna in בכורות. Bechoros. אמר אביי לא קשיא
הא דמקבל עליה אונסא וזולא. amar Abaye lo kashya ha demikabel alei
onsa uvisola. This is in a case where, and רש"י Rashi adds
in the word נכרי, nochri, the non-Jew accepted upon himself אונסא וזולא,
onsa uvisola, either אונס ones if it was totally, you know, unexpectedly
destroyed or זולא zola if the price went down. הא דלא קביל
עליה אונסא וזולא, ha d'lo kabil alei onsa uvisola, and in the
case where
it belongs to the owner,
to the נכרי, nochri, that's where he didn't accept the אונסא וזולא,
onsa uvisola, the depreciation or catastrophic loss. Right.
Now let's see which case is which. If he didn't accept אונסא
וזולא, onsa uvisola, then it sounds like... no, if he didn't accept
אונסא וזולא, onsa uvisola, that's the case in בכורות Bechoros because it
remains his. That is, he doesn't accept
fluctuation in... oh you're right, okay. Being
מקבל אונסא וזולא mekabel onsa uvisola means right, he took it upon
himself. So that's the liability. So if the liability, in the case
where he gave away the liability, that's our משנה, mishna, it belongs
to the Jew, and in the case where he did accept upon
himself liability, that was in בכורות. Bechoros. Okay. אמר ליה רבא, amar
lei Rava, so רבא Rava responds to אביי, Abaye, gonna disagree of
course. אי דקביל עליה מרה אונסא וזולא, ei d'kabil alei marei onsa
uvisola, if the owner accepted, the non-Jewish investor accepted upon himself אונסא
וזולא, onsa uvisola, צאן ברזל קרית ליה? tzon barzel karis lei? You're
going to... how can you call that צאן ברזל tzon barzel anymore?
I mean the whole point of צאן ברזל tzon barzel is that
you get a hundred percent stable investment. That's what makes it ברזל,
barzel, that's what makes it so solid. So רבא Rava doesn't like
that explanation of the משנה. mishna. ועוד, ve'od, and further, עד דתני
סיפא, ad detani seifa, because the סיפא seifa of the משנה mishna
says אבל מקבלין צאן ברזל מן העובד כוכבים, aval mekablin tzon barzel
min ha'akum, our משנה mishna says you are allowed to accept a
צאן ברזל tzon barzel investment from a non-Jew ולפלוג בדידי, veliflog bedidi,
so the סיפא seifa implies that
if you can accept it from a
non-Jew... What case are we talking about? In other words, why should
the בכור bechor be exempt from the laws of בכור, bechor, nonetheless,
it's permissible to charge a non-Jew this kind of interest, but forbidden
to charge a Jew this kind of interest? Okay, דלא קביל עליה
אונסא וזולא, delo kabil alei onsa vezola,
he did not accept אונסא וזולא, onsa vezola, that is, the liability
rests entirely on the Jewish partner. אבל קביל מרה אונסא וזולא, aval
kabil marei onsa vezola,
but however in a case of קביל מרה אונסא וזולא, kabil marei
onsa vezola, in a case where the non-Jewish investor, or the investor,
accepts upon himself אונסא וזולא, onsa vezola, שפיר דמי, shappir dami, it
would be okay for a Jewish investor even. That is, it wouldn't
be צאן ברזל tzon barzel anymore. That's a normal investment and that
would be okay. אלא אמר רבא, ela amar rava, how does רבא
Rava explain the משנה? mishnah? אידי ואידי דלא קבלה עליה מרה אונסא
וזולא. idi ve-idi delo kabla alei marei onsa vezola. Both משניות mishnayot
are talking about cases where the investor did not accept אונסא וזולא.
onsa vezola. The risk lies entirely on the מקבל. mekabel. לגבי בכורות,
legabi bechoros, היינו טעמא דולדות פטורים מן הבכורה, hainu ta'ama devladot pturim
min habechora,
the reason why the בכורות bechoros are exempt from בכור, bechor, a
special exemption by בכור, bechor, כיון דאי לאו האי זוזי אתי נכרי
תפיס לה לבהמה. keivan de'ilo hai zuzei ati nochri tapis lah lebehema.
If he's unable to pay back cash of the צאן ברזל tzon
barzel investment, then the non-Jew will just collect the sheep. ואי לא
משכח לה לבהמה, ve'ilo meshkach lah lebehema, and if the sheep aren't
around anymore—he's had them for ten years, all the sheep died—תפיס לה
לולדות, tapis lah levladot, he's going to take the children. Therefore, the
non-Jew still has a hand on the ability to claim the offspring,
and therefore they won't be בכור, bechor, והוה ליה יד נכרי באמצע.
vahavei lei yad nochri be'emtza. The hand of the non-Jew remains in
the pot, as it were. וכל יד נכרי באמצע פטור מן הבכורה.
vechol yad nochri be'emtza patur min habechora. And whenever the non-Jew has
a claim on the partnership, then it's פטור מן הבכורה patur min
habechora because special דין from בכור bechor because as long as the
non-Jewish person has a claim over it, it can't be a בכור
bechor because it's a partnership שותפות. shutfus. It's a joint ownership in
some sense; even very partially is enough to affect the laws of
בכור. bechor. One little interesting piece about בכור bechor and then I'm
going to have to go. There's a whole discussion about how does
בכור bechor work. בכור bechor seems like from most of the הלכות
halachos and most of the משניות, mishnayot, even from the תורה, Torah,
that it's קדוש מרחם. kadosh merachem. It becomes totally holy from the
time when it's born, from the time when it was conceived even,
in a sense. So then why is it that so many משניות
mishnayot and so many ברייתות beraitos talk about a person going to
be מקדיש makdish their בכור bechor actively, designating the בכור bechor a
level of קדושה? kedusha? And the ט"ז Taz discusses it at length
in יורה דעה Yoreh De'ah in הלכות בכור Hilchos Bechor and makes
a really, I think, beautiful point, which is that even though it's
holy intrinsically, a human being has a certain added role to play
in designating the קדושה kedusha further. And that's why there's no ברכה
bracha on doing the designating
of the בכור bechor animal, because it was partially done by God
and partially you're doing it yourself. And there's no way to kind
of claim that you're doing the whole מצוה mitzvah yourself by designating
the בכור bechor animal. רב סולובייצ'יק, Rav Soloveitchik, in one of the
יארצייט שיעורים, Yahrtzeit Shiurim, compared that to קידוש kiddush on
שבת. Shabbos. 100 percent. Well, and it's connected
also—the ברכה bracha issue, you have to see the ט"ז Taz there,
the explanation there is at length. But so on שבת, Shabbos, what
happens? שבת Shabbos comes in whether we like it or not; God
is in charge of שבת. Shabbos. It's holy on its own, nonetheless,
and we say מקדש השבת. mekadesh hashabbos. Nonetheless, our ability to say
קידוש, kiddush, our requirement to say קידוש, kiddush, is to somehow add
on to the קדושה kedusha of שבת Shabbos from our own participation
in that מצוה mitzvah as well. So, a nice little connection thinking
about how the קדושה kedusha intrinsic to the בכור bechor is קדוש
מרחם. kadosh merachem. God designated this animal as קדוש, kadosh, but at
the same time, a human being has some role to play in
a partnership with God in some sense. And there are other examples
of that as well. I think I remember it came up actually
somewhat recently; we had in the discussion of שמיטה shemitah there was
a few—maybe two weeks
ago—there's a question about the role of שמיטת כספים. shemitat kesafim. Whose
responsibility is it to give up the loan? Is it canceled by
God, אפקעתא דמלכא, afka'ata demalka, or is it a מצוה mitzvah for
the person who lent the money to forgive the loan? And I
think it's opinions quoted in the מרדכי Mordechai that says, well, really
it's automatic, but there's a מצוה mitzvah, that you have to do
it yourself anyway even though it happened automatically. So that's the same
kind of thing: something happens automatically—the קדושה kedusha or the forgiveness of
the loan happens automatically from God—and at the same time, we have
a responsibility, מצוה, to do it ourselves as well.
Why is there a ברכה bracha with the קידוש kiddush and not
with the...?
I'll show you the ט"ז Taz another time; it's a long ט"ז,
Taz, he kind of explains. Well, that's the whole with קידוש, kiddush,
it's not ברכת המצוות, birchat hamitzvot, but the same kind of question—you
have to see the explanation there and רב סולובייצ'יק Rav Soloveitchik's שיעור
shiur here, I think he deals with that.
But the יד נכרי באמצע פטור מן הבכורה yad nochri be'emtza patur
min habechora is interesting. Like, let's say I had a שותפות, shutfus,
I owned a flock with a non-Jew, could I be מקדיש makdish
an animal for a קרבן korban if he still had a...?
Oh, that's a different question.
coming active agency, different than בכורה, bechorah,
but still it's had a-
Right, has a different point, but the point about בכורה bechorah is
very relevant הלכה למעשה halacha l'maaseh because like I said, the whole
point is nowadays we don't want a bunch of בכורות bechorot running
around because we can't bring them as קרבנות. korbanot. So the practice
is whenever your animal is about to give birth to a what
might be a בכור bechor depending on the sex of the animal,
so you make a joint ownership with a non-Jewish person in order
to exempt the בכור, bechor, because otherwise you're going to have a
perfectly תמים tamim animal running around, it's going to have to be
brought as a קרבן, korban, you have this חיוב chiyuv and you
can't do it, you can't do anything with that sheep. So if
you make a joint ownership with a non-Jew and then buy it
back-
you could feed it, but you can't shear it, you can't let
it work, you have to just protect it and let it bring-
to be brought as a קרבן, korban, it would bring a lot
of complications. All right, have a great day everyone.